I want to have a conversation with you
this hour about a man called Jason Arday
who has been all over the news this
week. If you have been following this
story, you'll know it is one of the most
remarkable of our times, almost a
parable of our times, you might say. If
you haven't been following it, strap
yourself in cuz it's a hell of a yarn.
And what I want to explore with you is
who you think who or what you think is
to blame and what it tells us about our
society and some of the choices we have
made over recent years. Let me bring you
up to speed with the whole Jason story
in case you haven't been following it.
So this is a man who came to prominence
a few years ago in 2023 when he was
appointed as a professor at the
University of Cambridge and he became at
the time the youngest black professor
professor in Cambridge's history. He
taught in the sociology department um or
the education faculty but he was a
sociology teacher focusing on things
like critical race theory, deconalizing
the curriculum etc etc. And because of
his status as the youngest black
professor in Cambridge's history, he
attracted quite a lot of media
attention. The BBC covered his
appointment. He was invited on to
Question Time. He was a guest on Laura
Kunberg Sunday morning program on three
separate occasions. He was invited to
guest edit the Today program. He
appeared on a range of podcasts.
And people took at face value his claims
to be an academic pioneer. He was hailed
by the education faculty at the
University of Cambridge as the best in
the world at what he did.
But then a few weeks ago, allegations
started to emerge about academic
misconduct. So there were reports of
potential plagiarism in his PhD thesis.
There were questions about some of his
other research. Claims were raised about
whether he actually held some of the
visiting professorships at other top
universities that he had claimed. There
was even a suggestion that a book he had
said he had written didn't actually
exist at all. So people started to
question the academic integrity of
Professor Jason Arday.
But when these allegations were raised
there was a backlash. There was a rear
guard action from people at the
University of Cambridge, from his
college, Jesus College, Cambridge, and
[snorts] from other high-profile figures
largely on the left, who accused those
who raised these concerns about his
academic integrity, raised these
concerns about potential plagiarism of
racism.
There was an open letter signed by many
luminaries on the left organized by the
leftwing pressure group the Good Law
Project which essentially accused those
questioning Jason Arday's academic
credentials of being engaged in a
right-wing smear campaign.
Well, following that, further
revelations came to light, not just
about his academic credentials, but also
about some of his backstory. because
this is a man who would go on many a
podcast, many a media outlet and recount
a pretty remarkable life story. A life
story that by any measure would be if it
were true, and we'll come on to that,
remarkable. So, he said he was mute
until the age of 11. Couldn't speak
until the age of 11. He said he couldn't
read or write until the age of 18. He
made various claims about his medical
history, including being in a coma for
several months. uh he claimed to have
had a brain tumor, suffered with
epilepsy, had testicular cancer. He said
he experienced lockedin syndrome. He
also made remarkable claims about his
sporting prowess. Said he played at
youth level for Crystal Palace. Said he
was a very high level nineball pool
player. And what raised a lot of
eyebrows was his claim to have run 30
marathons in 35 days. The last nine of
which with a broken leg. This would have
made him not just a very impressive
endurance athlete, but one of the
greatest endurance athletes in human
history.
So, at this point, people started to
question his entire backstory. I mean,
there's so much to go through. He said
he was on the television program Seven
Up that you might remember back in the
day, despite the fact that it aired 20
years before he was even born.
So, people started going, "Hang on, this
Jason Arday, is he potentially a
plagiarist? Is he potentially a
fantasist?
And yet his defenders still insisted
that those questioning him were just
engaged in a right-wing smear tactic.
Now listen, when this story first broke,
I was a little bit conflicted and I took
a sort of more nuanced view because I do
think there are some on the right who
will jump on any story about someone
they perceive to be a DEI hire,
diversity, equity, inclusion. And we'll
come on to that and the impact it's
having in many of our institutions in a
moment. There are many who will jump on
such people and in quite an ugly and yes
at times racist way
try and press for their downfall. And I
think that is true. But at the same time
I thought there are too many on the left
who hold diverse candidates to a lower
standard and who are too quick to
dismiss credible allegations as just
smears. So I I took a somewhat nuanced
nuanced view to begin with
and then what changed is the news that a
Times higher education supplement
journalist a man called Jack Grove who
had been looking into Jason Arday's
academic track record and had been
emailing him emailing him questions
basically for a right of reply had been
reported to the police and the Met
police in their wisdom [snorts] decided
to launch a 4monl long investig
stigation into a journalist who had the
tmerity to email Jason Aday for a right
of reply to questions over his academic
integrity.
That is absolutely scandalous.
It is absurd.
And frankly, the fact that Mark Roelly
would not when being interviewed by Nick
Ferrari the other morning just apologize
for it. He said they dropped the ball.
Well, you can say that again. I'm I'm
afraid Marley, you owe Jack Grove an
apology. Are we living in a police
state? Do we investigate journalists to
just email a a top academic for a right
of reply? Is that really what we've sung
to? So that was the moment I became
really really angry because it became
more then than just a question about the
University of Cambridge appointing
someone who clearly should never have
been appointed. It became more than
media outlets like the BBC platforming
someone who clearly is an apparent
fantasist. it became broader because if
even the Metropolitan Police are so
quick to jump down the throats of people
asking legitimate questions because he
was crying racism, he alleged Jason Arde
when he reported this to the police that
it might have been racially motivated.
These questions being sent in by a Times
higher education journalist just saying,
"Look mate, we've got a few question
marks about whether you might have
plagiarized your PhD thesis." Entirely
legitimate questions. They were so
so craven to this culture of DEI that
has taken over that they launched a
4monl long investigation. That to me
says a lot about where we have gone
wrong as a country and I think this
brings us on to a broader question which
is has this entire DEI culture this
diversity equity inclusion culture and
let's call it what it is. It's a form of
discrimination is positive
discrimination is the oldfashioned term.
I mean in America they call it
affirmative action and I understand the
arguments for it which is that minority
groups have historically been
disadvantaged. So the way you address
that is that you give them a leg up now.
But the problem is I don't think you can
ever fix discrimination by replacing it
with discrimination of a different type.
And this is why what I want to explore
with you this hour is not only who's to
blame for this entire Jason Aard story,
but what you think it says about us and
whether you think the DEI culture has
gone too far. I have on one level a bit
of sympathy for Jason Aday. I think he's
as much a victim of DEI culture as
anything else because he was giving
these Cambridge academics kind of what
they wanted. They saw him as a quick way
out of their historic lack of diversity.
There's a remarkable remarkable
interview um when he was appointed of
Jason Arde Day. He's filmed by the BBC
with a woman called Hillary Kreman who's
the head of the education faculty at the
University of Cambridge. And the way she
sort of coups over him is remarkable and
it's deeply patronizing.
He uh she talks about him being
worldclass at what he does. She says,
"We're so lucky to have you." She talks
about him as if he is a kind of mascot
for Cambridge, as if he is a a
collectible, almost a trinket to be
wheeled out and displayed anytime anyone
accused Cambridge of a lack of
inclusion. And to me, it sums up the
soft bigotry of low expectations that
many on the left, I'm afraid, display.
You know, they like to accuse people on
the right of of being racist for just
raising valid questions about Jason
Aard's academic integrity. For me, the
real racists are the people who hold
diverse candidates to lower standards.
And I tell you who I feel really sorry
for, the many, many outstanding black
academics up and down this country who
will now because of the ineptitude of
Cambridge University be faced with
people looking at them and going, "Well,
are you just a diversity hire?" I mean,
this is the real problem with positive
discrimination with DEI. It fails
everyone. It fails the non-diverse
candidates who are denied opportunities
because they have been [sighs]
shunted to one side to make way for
someone who maybe doesn't actually meet
the the necessary criteria for the job,
but is promoted anyway. And it fails
people of color minority candidates who
genuinely do meet the criteria required
but who will forever more be tarnished
with the brush of being a diversity hire
and will be open to the suspicion that
they only got there through positive
discrimination.
Chem Bay recently talked about DEI
needing to be scrapped in some of our
public institutions. I think she is
right and I think unfortunately Jason
Arde who's become in a sense a poster
boy for the DEI movement. I think it
needs to be a landmark moment. I think
this is developing into a national
scandal because it incorporates our top
universities, the Metropolitan Police,
the BBC and the way they have all become
beholden to this DEI culture and it's
everywhere. I wrote about this for the
spectator this week and in the wake of
that article um I had a message from a
friend of mine who works in recruitment
and he said James you wouldn't believe
you wouldn't believe the extent to which
this DEI culture has taken over in the
recruitment practices of many many top
firms and he gave a few examples of
things that really really irritate him.
He said first of all it's just how
patronizing it is towards diverse
candidates. A lot of these recruiters
now who are thinking in a DEI mindset
are so patronizing. He he gave one
example of where people with neurode
divergence are being referred to in some
cases literally in the job applications
as superheroes with superpowers.
How patronizing. Someone's got, I don't
know, ADHD or autism and you're
referring to them as a super I mean
they're not Spider-Man. They've got
autism. I mean why are we using such
infantile patronizing language? we're
doing them a massive disservice. He
talked about employment lawyers being
too afraid to explain to DEI bosses that
some of their recruitment practices are
probably illegal, probably go beyond
positive action and actually break the
law and become discriminatory. He talks
about people having recruitment targets
for diverse candidates that bear no
resemblance to the wider population. for
example, a target to hire a certain
percentage of BME black and minority
ethnic candidates, even if it far
exceeds the percentage of the population
who are actually BME.
And I just think we need to explore to
what extent this is actually being
counterproductive. Who does this help?
Who does this help? No one. It helps no
one. It doesn't help diverse candidates
because they are then being left open to
the stigma that they might have not
ended up where they are through merit,
that they might have only got there
through special treatment. So, it's
unfair on them. It's unfair on people
who lose out otherwise.
And I just think it is dripping with a
kind of racism of its own. It is that
soft bigotry of low expectations. No
wonder you now have senior academics at
Cambridge circulating a letter demanding
an independent inquiry into our day's
appointment. They say the university
wanted a quick fix to improve the
diversity of its staff. And they're
right. Cambridge University cannot just
sweep this under the carpet. They need
to come out and explain themselves.
Forget about Jason Arane. He is on one
level, yes, he's brought this on
himself, but on one level, he's a victim
here. He gave the likes of Cambridge
University everything they wanted
because there's a type of sappy liberal
who looked at Jason Ardane and saw
everything they wanted to believe about
the world and themselves and they kind
of exploited him and the university
Jesus College Cambridge sort of
exploited him. Um Hillary Kreman the
head of the education faculty kind of
exploited him and and we need to be
hearing from them. They need to be
apologizing. They need to be explaining
themselves. Potentially, they need to be
resigning because this is outrageous.
Suki messages to say, "James, you're an
idiot. Beating the drum about DEI."
Okay, you have the odd example of where
it goes wrong. But have you ever
experienced a number of white hires who
are completely and utterly incompetent
but got promoted anyway? I'll give you
two examples, Liz Truss and Boris
Johnson.
Well, of course, Suki, no one is
disputing that incompetence is evenly
spread, and there are many incompetent
white people. and you give two examples
that in your view qualify for it. The
point is Boris Johnson and Liz Truss did
not become prime minister because they
were white. Jason Arde realistically, do
we think he would have been appointed
to a university professorship at
Cambridge if he was not a black man who
was studying critical race theory etc.
at a time in the wake of the Black Lives
Matter movement where universities were
trying to become more inclusive. That is
the problem. And clearly they lowered
their standards for him. They did no due
diligence. I mean, the the most generous
interpretation is that they just
completely dropped the ball on their
academic um standards, didn't check,
didn't validate his PhD, didn't actually
make sure it wasn't plagiarized. And the
worst interpretation is they simply
didn't care. They look the other way.
Maybe they suspected he was a fabulist.
You know, he was making stuff up about
his own life and potentially had
plagiarized his PhD, but thought doesn't
care. He'll make us look good. They saw
him like a kind of mascot, which is so
patronizing, so offensive. I just
honestly the more the more I've learned
about this story, the angrier I have
gotten. And I wonder what you think the
answers need to be. Uh Marcia is in
Hden. Good morning, Marcia. What would
you like to say?
>> Hi there. Good morning. Yeah, look, just
to say that I have to say I think some
of the language you've used this morning
is so offensive. Um, I think anyone
that's worked for any length of time
knows the idea of meritocracy is a
complete fantasy. The number of people
in jobs because their fathers were
barren or rich or they got an
opportunity to go to a posh school or
they have a friend of a friend that told
them about a job that nobody else saw
advertised. That doesn't excuse what I
It sounds like this guy was an absolute
fantasist. But the idea that you can say
that anybody that isn't what male and
white was only hired through DEI.
>> No, no, I'm not saying that. I'm not
saying that.
>> That's what I heard because the reality
is that people up and down the country
get jobs through all sorts of means,
especially now with AI. It's so
difficult to get a job. People are
trying everything they possibly can in
order to find out and put themselves in
the best position and and they they do
what they can. this guy. Yes, he does
sound like a fantasyist, but I think
that you're using what is clearly I mean
apparently he's autistic and there's all
sorts of stuff that there is a
difference between someone getting hired
and and finding out that that person
was, you know, was clearly lying about
their background and trying to slur
every single what person that that isn't
white and male that's got a job. No, I'm
No, I'm I'm making the exact opposite
point, Marcia, which is the problem is
stories like this fail. The I mean, if
we want to use academia as an example,
and no, there aren't enough black
academics currently, but there are many
outstanding ones. And those outstanding
black academics have been failed by this
story and by the fact that Jason Arde
was appointed because there will be
people looking at them now with the
suspicion of, well, were they just
diversity hires when they almost
certainly weren't. They were there on
merit. you that those people looking at
them are showing exactly the kind of
racism that we should fight against. How
about looking at him as a human being?
How about saying we have a human being
that was hired and clearly is a
fantasist? Why does it have to be about
the color of his skin or his race?
>> Because because because would he have
been appointed would he not would he
have been appointed to Cambridge at the
age of 37 as a professor? I mean his
only do you know what his actual um
university degree was in? It was in PE.
The guy's a PE teacher and he was
appointed as a university professor at
Cambridge because he had concocted this
remarkable life story, had allegedly
plagiarized a PhD. Um, and he was
focusing on issues that were kind of hot
button issues at the time. This was the
wake of the BLM movement, whatever. And
universities understandably were trying
to increase their diversity, but not not
in this way. I mean, this guy was a DEI
hire. would be amazed if if they if
their um recruitment process was so
slack that they were able to recruit
somebody who wasn't qualified to do the
job. I would be amazed if he was a the
only one and b it only related to
someone's color of their skin.
>> But do you think Jason Ar would have
been hired if he was white?
>> There were plenty of people hired and
white and not qualified to do.
>> That's a different question. Do you
think Jason Arde if he was white would
have been hired?
>> Don't assume that he would have been.
Yes. they still have to rely you have to
go through an interview and application
process there should be proper vetting
it's not easy to get these jobs and you
know I think what would be more helpful
is to look at what the recruitment
process was was put in place in order to
check this person's qualifications you
know presumably he had to you know have
appraisals and things to show whether he
was delivering against the job he was
actually in you don't just get the job
and they leave you for years so there's
a whole process around this and and I
just I think it's very it's kind of lazy
to make an assumption of this stuff. I
think it's better to understand what is
the process that employers have in place
to recruit.
>> Well, do we need do we need DEI
departments? Do we need DEI departments
in in big organizations in the public
sector? Because surely, look,
anti-discrimination laws, of course, we
need of course we need
anti-discrimination laws. You know, if
you say that you're not hiring someone
because of their skin color, that is
racist. That should be illegal. It is
illegal. But isn't the problem with DEI?
It is a form of positive discrimination.
You've had some employees, BBC for
example, they have in the past advertise
schemes and roles where only non-white
candidates can apply. Now, for me, that
is racism.
>> What um what they've been doing and what
the attempts to do is to address um
systemic
um inequalities are built into systems.
So what it looks at is it says things
like okay why is it for example um that
I don't know we're not we're not getting
any women applying for these particular
jobs um we have uh bias baked into our
system and look we found out that you
know we're not advertising fairly we're
not you know we're not advertising
across lots of different types of
channels um perhaps the only people we
promote in these jobs are from a certain
background and therefore other people
don't feel it's a job that they could
apply for. People still need the
qualifications. People still need to to
meet the job criteria. It's not that
>> well Jason clearly didn't.
>> I as I said I think that's why it's so
offensive because I think that you know
the idea that some type that the job
description wouldn't apply to you
because of the color of your skin is
deeply offensive.
>> Well, I don't think it did in Jason's
case, did it?
>> It's just not true. So it's very easy to
>> he is an extreme example of course which
is why it's made the headlines because
it's such an outrageous case but I do I
do wonder whether it is it speaks to
something broader
>> and I think somebody said before didn't
they about Liz trust but let let's use a
more modern example which is uh um Trump
you know the the idea that every single
leader that we see across the world is
the best person for that job they are
the most qualifying
>> there'll always be incompetent people
there will always be people who are not
up to that what you're not doing is
using that as an example. I mean,
imagine if you were to say um that Trump
was somehow the poster child for not
allowing any white American male in that
position of power.
>> No, but Maria Maria, you are absolutely
twisting my argument. [laughter] No,
you're imply you're implying that I'm
saying that because Jason Arday
shouldn't have been a professor that no
black academic should be appointed,
which is obviously not what I'm saying.
>> You said no DEI. said,
"Do you not agree? And the two are not
the same."
>> Do you not agree, Marcia? The talent is
evenly distributed. There are just as
many highly capable black people as
there are white people. And if we get
out the way, if there's no
discrimination, if we provide a level
playing field, then everyone should be
able to achieve on merit.
>> And that is exactly what DEI attempts to
do to level that playing field. That is
exactly the purpose. So why do many
employers have quotas for diverse
candidates that exceed for example the
population
>> because you don't understand what the
problem is if you don't count it. So how
do you know that there's an issue if you
don't answer the question to see if
there's an issue? That's the only reason
for it. You need the data and once you
have the data you can understand if
there is a problem. And you know if
there's no problem your DI will not be
putting in artificial arbitrary things
to solve something. It's only there if
an issue was